Finding Aid for Bertha Van Hoosen papers, 1880-1952
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Bertha Van Hoosen papers
1880-1952
Van Hoosen, Bertha, 1863-1952
86258 Aa 2; Ac
Physician from Rochester, Michigan and Chicago, Illinois. Correspondence, newspaper clippings, appointment books, diaries and miscellanea relating to student life at University of Michigan and her professional activities; also manuscript of autobiography, Petticoat Surgeon; and photographs.
3 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Dr. Sarah Van Hoosen Jones (donor no. 4427 ).
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Dr. Bertha Van Hoosen was born in 1863, in Rochester, Michigan. After she received her A.B. from the University of Michigan in 1884, she entered the University of Michigan Medical School, from which she graduated in 1888. Van Hoosen was awarded an honorary master's degree in 1912, and Loyola gave her an LL.D. in 1926. Dr. Van Hoosen's career includes a long list of surgical and hospital services. Following three years of private practice in Chicago, she became an attending gynecologist at Provident Hospital. She held that position until 1929. Van Hoosen also served at different times in the Woman's Hospital, Mary Thompson Hospital, Cook County Hospital, and the Frances E. Willard Hospital. She also held a professorship in the Woman's Medical College, Northwestern University, from 1894 until 1902. She then became a member of the medical staff of the University of Illinois Medical School. In 1919, she became professor and head of the Department of Obstetrics of Loyola University Medical School, retiring in 1937 as professor emeritus.
Dr. Van Hoosen was a fellow of the American College of Surgeons and a member of a long list of medical societies, as well as the Chicago Woman's Club, the Women's City Club, and a number of women's business and professional organizations. At the age of eighty-four, Van Hoosen wrote, "Petticoat Surgeon", which described her early difficulties in overcoming the prevailing prejudice against women doctors.
Van Hoosen died June 7, 1952.
The collection has been arranged into two series. The Van Hoosen - Jones Family series consists mainly of personal family correspondence among members of the Van Hoosen and Jones family. The Bertha Van Hoosen series consists of correspondence and other materials relating to the life and career of Dr. Van Hoosen. Included are materials from her years as a student at the University of Michigan, personal correspondence, and materials relating to her autobiography Petticoat Surgeon.
Subjects:
Chicago (Ill.); Medicine--Michigan--Rochester.; Physicians--Michigan--Rochester.; Rochester (Mich.); University of Michigan. Class of 1884.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Medicine and Surgery. Class of 1888.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1881-1890.StudentsSocial life and customs1881-1890.; Women physicians--Michigan.; Physicians--Illinois--Chicago.; Petticoat surgeon.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Blind persons.; Braille.; Clothing and dress--1881-1890.; Libraries--United States.; Physicians--Illinois--Chicago.; Physicians--Michigan--Rochester.; Reading.; Van Hoosen, Bertha, 1863-1952; Women.
Contributors:
American Medical Women's Association.; Jones, Joseph Comstock, d. 1897.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.; Watercolor paintings.
- Van Hoosen-Jones Family
  - Legal materials (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Undated (Box 1)
    - 1832, 1848-1870 (Box 1)
    - 1871-1880 (Box 1)
    - 1881-1889 (Box 1)
    - 1890-1892 (Box 1)
    - 1893-1896 (Box 1)
    - 1897-1900 (Box 1)
- Bertha Van Hoosen
  - Correspondence
    - Undated (Box 1)
    - 1880-1890 (Box 1)
    - 1891-1895 (Box 1)
    - 1896-1899 (Box 1)
    - 1900 (Box 1)
    - 1901-1910 (Box 1)
    - 1911-1920 (Box 1)
    - 1921-1930 (Box 1)
    - 1931-1940 (Box 1)
    - 1941-1947 (Box 1)
    - 1948 (Box 1)
    - 1949-1950 (Box 1)
    - 1951-1952 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper and magazine clippings, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Personal Writings (Box 1)
  - Royalty statements (Box 1)
  - Financial records-invoices, statements (Box 1)
  - Legal agreements for Petticoat Surgeon (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook (Box 1)
  - Pamphlet "Leaves from a Microbe's Notebook" (Box 1)
  - Address books, 2 volumes (Box 1)
  - Notebook of trip to Europe, undated (Box 2)
  - Appointment books and diaries
    - 1935 (Box 2)
    - 1937 (Box 2)
    - 1938 (Box 2)
    - 1946 (Box 2)
    - 1948 (Box 2)
    - 1949 (Box 2)
  - Medals (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook material (Box 2)
  - Manuscript of Petticoat Surgeon, 2 portfolios (Box 2)
  - Manuscript of Petticoat Surgeon, 3 portfolios (Box 3)
  - Photographs: portraits; photos of Van Hoosen with friends, and photos of Van Hoosen with woman reading a Braille text, 1880s (Box 3)
  - Diplomas, citations, etc. (Folder AC)
    (in oversize folder Ac)